<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Topics on Reducing Stereotype Threat Archive</title>
    <link>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Topics on Reducing Stereotype Threat Archive</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Definition</title>
      <link>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/definition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/definition/</guid>
      <description>Stereotype threat refers to being at risk of confirming, as self-characteristic, a negative stereotype about one&amp;rsquo;s group (Steele &amp;amp; Aronson, 1995). This term was first used by Steele and Aronson (1995) who showed in several experiments that Black college freshmen and sophomores performed more poorly on standardized tests than White students when their race was emphasized. When race was not emphasized, however, Black students performed better and equivalently with White students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vulnerable</title>
      <link>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/vulnerable/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/vulnerable/</guid>
      <description>Since the publication of Steele and Aronson&amp;rsquo;s (1995) study, researchers have identified risk factors that increase one’s vulnerability to stereotype threat—one&amp;rsquo;s “stereotype vulnerability” (Aronson, 2002). Although these factors might be less influential than the situational factors, there are some chronic differences in individuals and groups that might increase susceptibility to stereotype threat.
Group membership In some respects, everyone is vulnerable to stereotype threat, at least in some circumstances. Everyone belongs to at least one group that is characterized by some sort of stereotype, and any salient social identity can affect performance on a task that offers the possibility that a stereotype might be confirmed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Situations</title>
      <link>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/situations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/situations/</guid>
      <description>Although some individuals are more susceptible to stereotype threat than others, stereotype threat is also more common in some situations than others. Research suggests that stereotype threat is more likely to occur in the following contexts.
Group identity salience When one’s stereotyped group status is made relevant or conspicuous by situational features, stereotype threat and performance decrements are more likely. Because stereotype threat arises from negative performance expectations in a specific domain, any group can show evidence of underperformance if the situation brings attention to the threatened identity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Consequences</title>
      <link>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/consequences/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/consequences/</guid>
      <description>Stereotype threat produces numerous consequences, most of which are negative in nature. Many studies have replicated and extended the finding first reported by Steele and Aronson (1995) that invoking group memberships associated with stereotypes can harm performance on tasks where poor performance might confirm stereotypes. Subsequent work has broadened to examine performance on many different tasks and a variety of consequences. Here we review the major consequences of stereotype threat that have been identified in research to date.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/mechanisms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/mechanisms/</guid>
      <description>Stereotype threat effects have been shown in many different situations involving a variety of stereotypes. Although stereotype threat effects appear to be robust, the specific mechanisms by which stereotype threat harms performance is still not entirely clear. This ambiguity likely reflects that fact that stereotype threat probably produces several different consequences, each of which can contribute to decreased performance (Steele, Spencer, &amp;amp; Aronson, 2002). Steele and Aronson (1995), for example, speculated that distraction, narrowed attention, anxiety, self-consciousness, withdrawal of effort, or even overeffort might all play a role.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reduce</title>
      <link>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/reduce/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/reduce/</guid>
      <description>Stereotype threat effects have been demonstrated in many studies using different tests and tasks. However, research has also shown that performance deficits can be reduced or eliminated by several means.
Reframing the task One method that has been shown to reduce stereotype threat is to &amp;ldquo;reframe&amp;rdquo; or use different language to describe the task or test being used. Stereotype threat arises in situations where task descriptions highlight social identities stereotypically associated with poor performance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criticisms</title>
      <link>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/criticisms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/criticisms/</guid>
      <description>Several issues surrounding stereotype threat have been critiqued.
Overreliance on college student samples Many of the first studies on stereotype threat were conducted with college students, and Whaley (1998) suggested that &amp;ldquo;research on college populations may be too narrow a base on which to rest social psychological theories of human behavior&amp;rdquo; (p. 679). However, the literature on stereotype threat is now replete with studies that have drawn from broader and more diverse populations and from many different settings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unresolved</title>
      <link>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/unresolved/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://sites-garcias.c9users.io/topics/unresolved/</guid>
      <description>There are several issues that are currently unresolved that would appear to benefit from additional theoretical refinement or empirical attention.
What exactly is stereotype threat? Although people reliably perform more poorly under stereotype threat, there is a surprising degree of variability in defining exactly what stereotype threat represents. Steele and Aronson (1995) originally defined stereotype threat as &amp;ldquo;being at risk of confirming, as self-characteristic, a negative stereotype about one&amp;rsquo;s group&amp;rdquo; (p.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>