<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Reducing Stereotype Threat Archive on Reducing Stereotype Threat Archive</title>
    <link>https://garcias.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in The Reducing Stereotype Threat Archive on Reducing Stereotype Threat Archive</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 17:25:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://garcias.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Definition</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/topics/definition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/topics/definition/</guid>
      <description>Stereotype threat refers to being at risk of confirming, as self-characteristic, a negative stereotype about one&amp;rsquo;s group (Steele &amp;amp; Aronson, 1995). This term was first used by Steele and Aronson (1995) who showed in several experiments that Black college freshmen and sophomores performed more poorly on standardized tests than White students when their race was emphasized. When race was not emphasized, however, Black students performed better and equivalently with White students.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vulnerable</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/topics/vulnerable/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/topics/vulnerable/</guid>
      <description>Since the publication of Steele and Aronson&amp;rsquo;s (1995) study, researchers have identified risk factors that increase one’s vulnerability to stereotype threat—one&amp;rsquo;s “stereotype vulnerability” (Aronson, 2002). Although these factors might be less influential than the situational factors, there are some chronic differences in individuals and groups that might increase susceptibility to stereotype threat.
Group membership In some respects, everyone is vulnerable to stereotype threat, at least in some circumstances. Everyone belongs to at least one group that is characterized by some sort of stereotype, and any salient social identity can affect performance on a task that offers the possibility that a stereotype might be confirmed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Situations</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/topics/situations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/topics/situations/</guid>
      <description>Although some individuals are more susceptible to stereotype threat than others, stereotype threat is also more common in some situations than others. Research suggests that stereotype threat is more likely to occur in the following contexts.
Group identity salience When one’s stereotyped group status is made relevant or conspicuous by situational features, stereotype threat and performance decrements are more likely. Because stereotype threat arises from negative performance expectations in a specific domain, any group can show evidence of underperformance if the situation brings attention to the threatened identity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Consequences</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/topics/consequences/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/topics/consequences/</guid>
      <description>Stereotype threat produces numerous consequences, most of which are negative in nature. Many studies have replicated and extended the finding first reported by Steele and Aronson (1995) that invoking group memberships associated with stereotypes can harm performance on tasks where poor performance might confirm stereotypes. Subsequent work has broadened to examine performance on many different tasks and a variety of consequences. Here we review the major consequences of stereotype threat that have been identified in research to date.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/topics/mechanisms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/topics/mechanisms/</guid>
      <description>Stereotype threat effects have been shown in many different situations involving a variety of stereotypes. Although stereotype threat effects appear to be robust, the specific mechanisms by which stereotype threat harms performance is still not entirely clear. This ambiguity likely reflects that fact that stereotype threat probably produces several different consequences, each of which can contribute to decreased performance (Steele, Spencer, &amp;amp; Aronson, 2002). Steele and Aronson (1995), for example, speculated that distraction, narrowed attention, anxiety, self-consciousness, withdrawal of effort, or even overeffort might all play a role.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reduce</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/topics/reduce/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/topics/reduce/</guid>
      <description>Stereotype threat effects have been demonstrated in many studies using different tests and tasks. However, research has also shown that performance deficits can be reduced or eliminated by several means.
Reframing the task One method that has been shown to reduce stereotype threat is to &amp;ldquo;reframe&amp;rdquo; or use different language to describe the task or test being used. Stereotype threat arises in situations where task descriptions highlight social identities stereotypically associated with poor performance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Criticisms</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/topics/criticisms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/topics/criticisms/</guid>
      <description>Several issues surrounding stereotype threat have been critiqued.
Overreliance on college student samples Many of the first studies on stereotype threat were conducted with college students, and Whaley (1998) suggested that &amp;ldquo;research on college populations may be too narrow a base on which to rest social psychological theories of human behavior&amp;rdquo; (p. 679). However, the literature on stereotype threat is now replete with studies that have drawn from broader and more diverse populations and from many different settings.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unresolved</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/topics/unresolved/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/topics/unresolved/</guid>
      <description>There are several issues that are currently unresolved that would appear to benefit from additional theoretical refinement or empirical attention.
What exactly is stereotype threat? Although people reliably perform more poorly under stereotype threat, there is a surprising degree of variability in defining exactly what stereotype threat represents. Steele and Aronson (1995) originally defined stereotype threat as &amp;ldquo;being at risk of confirming, as self-characteristic, a negative stereotype about one&amp;rsquo;s group&amp;rdquo; (p.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Walsh, Hickey, &amp; Duffy, 1999</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/walsh_hickey_duffy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/walsh_hickey_duffy/</guid>
      <description>Two studies examined whether test item content might play a role in stereotype threat. In Experiment 1, male and female students in grades 7-8 completed math story problems that were identical but used either male names, female names, or featured names not gender specific (control). Performance was significantly better when males names were used, but students with lower math scores were more likely to correctly answer items with female names. There were no significant effects due to students&amp;rsquo; gender.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Walton &amp; Cohen, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/walton_cohen_2003/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/walton_cohen_2003/</guid>
      <description>This paper reports a meta-analysis of studies on stereotype threat with a focus on the performance of groups who might be advantaged by an invoked stereotype (e.g., men in mathematics, African-Americans in athletics). The boosting of performance from an awareness that an outgroup is negatively stereotyped is called stereotype lift. The meta-analysis showed that stereotype lift produces improved performance in any context where the ability or worth of an outgroup is impugned, regardless of the means by which this is done.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Walton &amp; Cohen, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/walton_cohen_2007/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/walton_cohen_2007/</guid>
      <description>Two experiments examined how doubts about belonging, or belonging uncertainty, can arise under stereotype threat. Specifically, it was hypothesized that people who are stigmatized in a domain are less certain of the strength of their social bonds and more sensitive to information about social connections in that domain. In Experiment 1, Black and White undergraduates were asked to think of eight friends, two friends, or no friends who would fit well in a college computer science program.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wicherts, Dolan, &amp; Hessen, 2005</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/wicherts_dolan_hessen/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/wicherts_dolan_hessen/</guid>
      <description>These experiments conceptualize stereotype threat as a source of measurement bias in testing, allowing use of mathematical modeling to separate latent from measured variables. To allow this modeling in Experiment 1, White and minority Dutch high school students completed a multi-faceted test that was described either as pertaining to their interests and abilities (control) or, additionally, as an &amp;ldquo;intelligence test&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for minority students). In addition, students in the stereotype threat condition completed a form regarding their ethnicity before taking the exam, whereas students in the control condition did so after taking the exam.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wout, Danso, Jackson, &amp; Spencer, 2008</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/wout_danso_jackson_spencer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/wout_danso_jackson_spencer/</guid>
      <description>Two experiments were designed to distinguish different kinds of stereotype threat based on their source. Specifically, the study addressed whether stereotype threat that either focused on the group (group-threat) or on the performance of the individual group member (self-threat) might occur in different situations and be influenced by different factors. To test these possibilities, female undergraduates in Experiment 1 completed a difficult math test in one of four conditions: when the test was described as non-diagnostic of their ability (non-diagnostic control), when it was described as diagnostic of their abilities (traditional stereotype threat), when it was diagnostic but that they would grade their own test and results would be anonymous (self-threat), or when the test was diagnostic and would be used to assess average performance of men and women with little regard to their individual score (group-threat).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yeung &amp; von Hippel, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/yeung_vonhippel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/yeung_vonhippel/</guid>
      <description>This paper examines stereotype threat effects involved in driving ability. In Experiment 1, female university students with an average of several years experience completed a driving exercise on a simulator. Some women were told that the study was designed to assess &amp;ldquo;mental processes involved in driving&amp;rdquo; (control) whereas the other women were told that the study was to &amp;ldquo;investigate the reasons that men are better drivers than women&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat). Although women in the two groups showed equivalent driving quality in terms of maintaining proper speed and road orientation, women in the stereotype threat condition were more than twice as likely to hit a pedestrian jaywalker who unexpectedly appeared near the end of the simulation (59% vs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yopyk &amp; Prentice, 2005</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/yopyk_prentice/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/yopyk_prentice/</guid>
      <description>These experiments examined the effects of dual social identities and task framing on stereotype threat. In Experiment 1, college student-athletes described their latest academic success (student identity highlighted), their latest athletic competition (athlete identity highlighted), or provided directions from their dorm to the campus library (control), then completed measures of self-regard and a difficult math test. Students performed more poorly on the test when their identity as athletes had been highlighted compared with the other two conditions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>von Hippel, von Hippel, Conway, Preacher, Schooler, &amp; Radvansky, 2005</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/vonhippel_vonhippel_conway_preacher_schooler_radvansky/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/vonhippel_vonhippel_conway_preacher_schooler_radvansky/</guid>
      <description>This set of experiments address the impact of impression management motivation on coping with stereotype threat. It was hypothesized that individuals who are high in impression management (i.e., those individuals who chronically deny negative, but claim positive, self-attributes in a given context) would be most likely to deny stereotype threat either by denying that a stereotype is accurate (a collective strategy) or by denying that it is self-relevant (an individualistic strategy).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Smith &amp; White, 2002</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/smith_white/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/smith_white/</guid>
      <description>These two study examined whether the means by which stereotypes are highlighted affect test performance. In Experiment 1, White female undergraduates indicated their degree of identification with math then completed what they were told was a &amp;ldquo;new math instrument.&amp;rdquo; One third of the participants then completed the math test (implicit stereotype threat). The other students were told that &amp;ldquo;men are better at mathematics than women&amp;hellip;maybe a result of biological differences&amp;rdquo; and either that &amp;ldquo;our own investigations [with this instrument] found similar results&amp;rdquo; (explicit stereotype threat) or &amp;ldquo;our results show that there are no gender differences on [this instrument]&amp;rdquo; (stereotype nullification).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Smith, Sansone, &amp; White, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/smith_sansone_white/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/smith_sansone_white/</guid>
      <description>These experiments assess the impact of stereotype threat on task interest, a strong predictor of long-term persistence in a given domain. In Experiment 1, high achievement-oriented female undergraduates who had not yet selected an academic major were asked to complete an &amp;ldquo;computing aptitude assessment tool&amp;rdquo; that either had or had not produced results showing that men are superior to women in mathematics (stereotype threat vs. control). Some students were given an individual performance goal (&amp;ldquo;this aptitude tool will really show what you can do&amp;rdquo;) and these students were told either to avoid poor performance (performance-avoidance goal) or to strive for positive performance (performance-approach goal).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spencer, Steele, &amp; Quinn, 1999</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/spencer_steele_quinn/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/spencer_steele_quinn/</guid>
      <description>Three experiments addressed the performance of women on mathematics tests under varying contexts. In Experiment 1, women and men who were highly identified with mathematics (i.e., had a history of successful performance and valued performance in math) completed an easy or difficult math exam. Performance was equivalent when the test was relatively easy, but men outperformed women when the test was difficult. In Experiment 2, all participants completed the same set of mathematical items, but they were told either that the test they would or would not produce gender differences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stangor, Carr, &amp; Kiang, 1998</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/stangor_carr_kiang/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/stangor_carr_kiang/</guid>
      <description>These two experiments examined the consequences of stereotype activation on expectations of performance. Students in these experiments expected to complete two tasks but actually completed only one. After students completed the first task involving finding words in an array of letters, they were told either that they did well or relatively poorly on the task. They then were told that they would complete a second test but, prior to doing so, were asked to estimate how well they would perform.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Steele &amp; Aronson, 1995</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/steele_aronson/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/steele_aronson/</guid>
      <description>This paper raised the possibility that culturally-shared stereotypes suggesting poor performance of certain groups can, when made salient in a context involving the stereotype, disrupt performance of an individual who identifies with that group. This effect was termed stereotype threat, and the existence and consequences of stereotype threat were investigated in four experiments. Experiment 1 involved African American and White college students who took a difficult test using items from the GRE Verbal exam under one of two conditions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Steele, James, &amp; Barnett, 2002</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/steele_james_barnett/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/steele_james_barnett/</guid>
      <description>This correlational study examined views of undergraduate women in male-dominated academic fields. A representative sample of first-year and fourth-year men and women were invited to complete a survey about students&amp;rsquo; experiences and aspirations. Included were items focusing on perceived sex discrimination and stereotype threat, identification with their academic major, and the desire to change their major. Results showed that women in male-dominated majors were more likely to report gender discrimination, expected more future discrimination, and perceived more stereotype threat than did women in majors not dominated by men.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stone &amp; McWhinnie, 2008</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/stone_mcwhinnie/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/stone_mcwhinnie/</guid>
      <description>This study examined the impact of subtle versus blatant presentation of stereotype threat cues. Subtle and blatant cues were hypothesized to affect performance for different reasons and to emerge on different measures. Subtle cues might cause individuals under stereotype threat to focus resources on reducing uncertainty about bias. To the degree that this causes attention to be directed away from the task, performance on skills requiring concentration and accuracy should be harmed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stone, 2002</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/stone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/stone/</guid>
      <description>Stereotype threat can lead individuals to reduce their effort or preparation even though doing so might harm performance, a phenomenon known as &amp;ldquo;self-handicapping.&amp;rdquo; In Experiment 1, white college students were asked to complete a task based on golf that was described either as reflecting &amp;ldquo;factors correlated with natural athletic ability&amp;rdquo; (high stereotype threat) or &amp;ldquo;factors correlated with general sports performance&amp;rdquo; (low stereotype threat). Before completing the task, students were allowed to practice as long as they liked.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stone, Lynch, Sjomeling, &amp; Darley, 1999</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/stone_lynch_sjomeling_darley/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/stone_lynch_sjomeling_darley/</guid>
      <description>In these studies, Black and White undergraduates were asked to complete a task involving golf skills, but the description of the task was varied to create a condition of stereotype threat for each group in one condition. In Experiment 1, participants were led to believe either that the task required natural sports ability or required athletic intelligence. Based on culturally-shared stereotypes, these descriptions should introduce stereotype threat for White and Black participants, respectively.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stricker &amp; Bejar, 2004</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/stricker_bejar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/stricker_bejar/</guid>
      <description>In this study, the difficulty of items constituting a standardized test were varied to assess the impact on stereotype threat. Given that research suggests that stereotype threat is more pronounced on difficult than easy tests (Spencer, Steele, &amp;amp; Quinn, 1999), these researchers hypothesized that reducing the difficulty of items on the GRE General Test might reduce or eliminate stereotype threat effects. The sample included White and Blacks students of both genders who were college seniors or first-year graduate students and who agreed to take a computerized GRE General test and to answer some questions about the test.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stricker &amp; Ward, 2004</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/stricker_ward/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/stricker_ward/</guid>
      <description>This paper reports on two field studies examining the consequence of making inquiries about ethnicity prior to taking the Advanced Placement Calculus examination and the Computerized Placement Test. In Experiment 1, individuals who were taking the AP Calculus AB Examination either completed the standard answer sheet that inquires about the test taker&amp;rsquo;s race and gender (control, n = 897) or responded to an answer sheet with those sections masked (experimental, n = 755).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoman, White, Yamawaki, &amp; Koishi, 2008</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/thoman_white_yamawaki_koishi/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/thoman_white_yamawaki_koishi/</guid>
      <description>This experiment examined whether highlighting different aspects of a stereotype might affect the consequences of stereotype activation. Specifically, it was speculated that stereotype threat regarding women&amp;rsquo;s math performance might rest on the implication that women differ from men in their inherent ability in math rather than their effort. To see whether highlighting different aspects of a gender stereotype would influence performance, female undergraduates completed a difficult math test under one of three conditions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vick, Seery, Blascovich, &amp; Weisbuch, 2008</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/vick_seery_blascovich_weisbuch/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:19 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/vick_seery_blascovich_weisbuch/</guid>
      <description>This experiment measured physiological responses in different testing conditions to assess whether individuals viewed a difficult test as challenging (when resources are seen as adequate for successful task completion) or threatening (when resources are seen as inadequate for successful task completion). Whereas challenges tends to decrease systemic vascular resistance and to increase cardiac output, threat increases vascular resistance but produces minimal change in cardiac output. To examine these physiological responses to task demands, the researchers had male and female undergraduates complete a difficult math test that was described as typically producing gender differences (invoking stereotype threat for women) or no gender differences (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rydell, McConnell, &amp; Beilock, in press</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/rydell_mcconnell_beilock/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/rydell_mcconnell_beilock/</guid>
      <description>Four experiments assessed how highlighting multiple identities with divergent implications for task performance can affect stereotype threat effects. In Experiment 1, female undergraduates completed a math test after receiving information highlighting their gender (stereotype threat), their status as a college student (a group that stereotypically is good at math), both group memberships (multiple identity), or no information about their social identities (control). Math performance was poorest in the condition in which gender was highlighted, but performance in the condition where multiple identities were highlighted was equivalent with the control condition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sawyer &amp; Hollis-Sawyer, 2005</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/sawyer_hollis-sawyer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/sawyer_hollis-sawyer/</guid>
      <description>This study examined the influence of individual difference and contextual factors on performance on a test of cognitive ability. Male and female university students completed a battery of personality questionnaires designed to assess Neuroticism, Extroversion, Openness, Agreeableness, and Conscientiousness, and a scale to assess belief in the malleability of intelligence. In addition, the students were told that the upcoming test was either diagnostic of general cognitive ability (high stereotype threat) or that it was an interest measure (low stereotype threat) and that the test was relevant to acquiring a job as postal clerk (low face validity) or as a geometry teacher (high face validity).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schimel, Arndt, Banko, &amp; Cook, 2004</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/schimel_arndt_banko_cook/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/schimel_arndt_banko_cook/</guid>
      <description>This paper examines whether different kinds of self-affirmation are differentially effective in protecting individuals from stereotype threat. Specifically, three studies assessed if affirmations highlighting on one&amp;rsquo;s intrinsic self-worth (focusing on valued intrinsic self-aspects, such as unconditional relationships and important personal values) might be more effective than affirmations highlighting one&amp;rsquo;s extrinsic self-worth (focusing on valued extrinsic self-aspects, such as conditionally accepting relationships and imposed social standards). In Experiment 1, male and female undergraduates were randomly assigned to complete sentence fragments referring to the self to provide an intrinsic (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schmader &amp; Johns, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/schmader_johns/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/schmader_johns/</guid>
      <description>This paper reports three studies examining the role of working memory capacity in stereotype threat. Working memory capacity refers to a memory system responsible for focusing attention on task-relevant information while inhibiting task-irrelevant thoughts. Effective utilization of working memory capacity is central for successful performance on cognitive tasks, and failures in working memory had been suggested as responsible for performance decrements under stereotype threat. These studies provided the most direct test to date of the possibility that stereotype threat might diminish working memory capacity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schmader, 2002</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/schmader/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/schmader/</guid>
      <description>This study examined the moderating role of group identification on stereotype threat. Steele &amp;amp; Aronson (1995) and others had shown that individuals are more likely to show performance decrements under conditions creating stereotype threat when they strongly identify with the domain in question (e.g., women who strongly identified with the domain of mathematics). This study sought to test whether the strength of one&amp;rsquo;s group identification might also play a role (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Schmader, Johns, &amp; Barquissau, 2004</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/schmader_johns_barquissau/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/schmader_johns_barquissau/</guid>
      <description>Two experiments assessed the impact of individuals&amp;rsquo; stereotype endorsement on their performance under stereotype threat. In Experiment 1, women undergraduates who were majoring in a math-related field completed a survey in which they were asked about their endorsement of stereotypes (e.g., &amp;ldquo;In general, men may be better than women at math&amp;rdquo;), the legitimacy of gender-based status differences (e.g., &amp;ldquo;Differences in status between men and women are fair&amp;rdquo;), their perceptions of their own ability, confidence, and self-esteem in math, and their intentions of continuing in the field of mathematics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seibt &amp; Förster, 2004</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/seibt_forster/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/seibt_forster/</guid>
      <description>These studies examined the possibility that exposure to different types of stereotypes might change one&amp;rsquo;s regulatory focus (Higgins, 1998), thereby altering means by which an individual attempts to solve problems. Specifically, it was suggested that positive stereotypes might induce a promotion focus engendering approach or eagerness strategies, and negative stereotypes might induce a prevention focus encouraging avoidance or vigilance strategies. To test these ideas, Experiment 1 had male and female undergraduates not majoring in psychology complete a proofreading task.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sekaquaptewa &amp; Thompson, 2002</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/sekaquaptewa_thompson/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/sekaquaptewa_thompson/</guid>
      <description>Two experiments examined the role of solo status on stereotype threat. Although many field studies had suggested that performance of women and ethnic minorities was undermined in relation to their numerical minority status, most lab studies had not. These researchers suspected that these seemingly discrepant findings had emerged because field studies usually focused on minority status at the time of performance whereas lab studies had typically focused on the time of learning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sekaquaptewa &amp; Thompson, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/sekaquaptewa_thompson_2003/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/sekaquaptewa_thompson_2003/</guid>
      <description>This experiment compared performance of women under solo versus non-solo status conditions under conditions designed to create or undermine stereotype threat. White male and female undergraduates learned math-related information that was later to be shared with a group. Students were told either that the material was &amp;ldquo;traditional math&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for women) or were assured that &amp;ldquo;men and women perform equally well on this type of material&amp;rdquo; (control). After studying the information, students then were asked to take turns answering questions about the information in the presence of three men or three women.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sekaquaptewa, Waldman, &amp; Thompson, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/sekaquaptewa_waldman_thompson/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/sekaquaptewa_waldman_thompson/</guid>
      <description>Two experiments examined the role of solo status on identity salience. It was hypothesized that solo status would tend to increase collective self-construal (i.e., a self-view that one represents one&amp;rsquo;s group and that one&amp;rsquo;s actions might reflect on their group). In Experiment 1, White and Black college students were given information that would supposedly be used in an upcoming study they would complete with some other students. Each student was then given photographs of the other students, and the composition of these photo sets was used to manipulate solo status.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shih, Ambady, Richeson, Fujita, &amp; Gray, 2002</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/shih_ambady_richeson_fujita_gray/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/shih_ambady_richeson_fujita_gray/</guid>
      <description>These studies focused on whether the subtlety of stereotype activation influences how individuals are affected by positive stereotypes. In Experiment 1, Asian-American students completed a survey about their entertainment preferences (control), one focusing on their ethnic identity without invoking stereotypes (subtle activation), or a questionnaire that asked about their beliefs regarding the commonality and validity of stereotypes associated with Asian-Americans (blatant activation). Performance on a subsequent math task was better in the subtle activation compared with the control and blatant stereotype conditions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shih, Bonam, Sanchez, &amp; Peck, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/shih_bonam_sanchez_peck/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/shih_bonam_sanchez_peck/</guid>
      <description>These experiments examined stereotype threat processes in mono- versus multi-racial individuals. It was hypothesized that biracial individuals might suppress racial stereotypes in conditions in which race is salient. Experiment 1 had multiracial, White, and Minority students complete a questionnaire about attitudes concerning race. Multiracial individuals were less likely to see race as a barrier, to report that their parents emphasized race, and to believe that race can bilogically determine personality or ability, and were more comfortable pursuing intimate relationships with people of a different racial background compared with monoracial individuals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shih, Pittinsky, and Ambady, 1999</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/shih_pittinsky_ambady/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/shih_pittinsky_ambady/</guid>
      <description>Two studies examined how intellectual performance can be moderated by highlighting different stereotyped social identities. In Experiment 1, Asian-American undergraduates completed a math task after responding to a survey questionnaire designed to highlight ethnicity but that did not explicitly refer to stereotypes. The survey focused on students&amp;rsquo; ethnic identity, their gender identity, or neither identity. This manipulation is particularly interesting because one identity (&amp;ldquo;woman&amp;rdquo;) is typically negatively stereotyped but the other (&amp;ldquo;Asian&amp;rdquo;) is typically positively stereotyped in quantitative domains.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shih, Pittinsky, and Trahan, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/shih_pittinsky_trahan/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/shih_pittinsky_trahan/</guid>
      <description>These studies examined how performance on a verbal task can be moderated by varying the salience of social identities. In Experiment 1, female Asian-American undergraduates completed a survey designed to highlight their ethnic identity, their gender identity, or their identity as a student. After completing one of the surveys, the students were told that they would complete a task assessing their verbal ability, inducing possible stereotype threat based on Asian identity and possibly stereotype lift based on female identity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Osborne &amp; Walker, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/osborne_walker/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/osborne_walker/</guid>
      <description>This study focused on incoming students at a racially diverse inner-city high school in the Midwest of the United States. Identification with academics was measured and correlated with GPAs, levels of absenteeism, behavioral problems, and retention levels. Regardless of race, the students who valued and viewed academics as central to the self had higher grades, less absenteeism, and fewer behavioral referrals. Among students of color, however, those who most identified with academics were most likely to withdraw from school.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Osborne, 1995</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/osborne_1995/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/osborne_1995/</guid>
      <description>This correlation study examined the notion that African-Americans sense of worth becomes increasingly disconnected from academic performance to the degree that poor performance in academics can confirm negative stereotypes regarding intellectual ability. This phenomenon, termed disidentification, suggests that African-Americans begin with strong identity attachments to academics but are increasingly likely to detach their self-esteem from such pursuits over time. To test these hypotheses, data regarding African-American and White students&amp;rsquo; self-esteem and GPA in 8th and 10th grades were drawn from the National Education Longitudinal Study.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Osborne, 1997</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/osborne_1997/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/osborne_1997/</guid>
      <description>This correlation study follows on the author&amp;rsquo;s previous work (Osborne, 1995) showing that African-American boys, but not African-American girls or Whites, disidentify from academics over time. As in that earlier study, data regarding self-esteem and GPA were drawn from the National Education Longitudinal Study. This study, however, focused on Hispanic students in addition to White and African-American students, and data from 8th, 10th, and 12th grades were examined to see if girls might disidentify later in their school careers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Osborne, 2001</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/osborne/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/osborne/</guid>
      <description>This experiment examined whether anxiety might account for racial differences in academic performance and gender differences in math performance under stereotype threat. Data reflecting the performance of approximately 28,000 high school seniors on vocabulary, reading, and mathematics were drawn from a national database. The database also included students self-reports of anxiety they experienced when taking the tests. Results showed that whites tended to outperform blacks on these tests and also experienced less anxiety when taking them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Osborne, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/osborne_2006/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/osborne_2006/</guid>
      <description>This experiment assessed whether stereotype threat can produce physiological arousal and cognitive disruptions that might differentially affect men&amp;rsquo;s and women&amp;rsquo;s performance in math. Male and female undergraduates were told that they would complete a difficult math test after being told &amp;ldquo;girls score lower in math tests than boys&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for women) or, for half the participants, additionally that &amp;ldquo;there are many cases where girls score as well or better than boys&amp;hellip;these tests have never shown gender differences&amp;rdquo; (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Osborne, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/osborne_2007/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/osborne_2007/</guid>
      <description>This experiment followed on the author&amp;rsquo;s previous research (Osborne, 2006) assessing whether stereotype threat can produce physiological arousal and cognitive disruptions that might differentially affect men&amp;rsquo;s and women&amp;rsquo;s performance in math. As in that previous study, male and female undergraduates were told that they would complete a difficult math test after being told &amp;ldquo;girls score lower in math tests than boys&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for women) or, for half the participants, additionally that &amp;ldquo;there are many cases where girls score as well or better than boys&amp;hellip;these tests have never shown gender differences&amp;rdquo; (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oswald &amp; Harvey, 2000/2001</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/oswald_harvey/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/oswald_harvey/</guid>
      <description>This study examined the impact of exposure to derogatory cartoons about women&amp;rsquo;s abilities in math on performance on math problems. Female undergraduates entered a laboratory in which, in one condition, there hung a cartoon depicting a woman struggling to answer an easy math problem while a man solves a difficult math problem (stereotype threat for women). In the other condition, there was no cartoon on the wall (control). Students were told that they would complete a difficult math test after being told either &amp;ldquo;males and females do equally well on this test&amp;rdquo; or nothing about gender differences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ployhart, Ziegert, &amp; McFarland, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/ployhart_ziegert_mcfarland/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/ployhart_ziegert_mcfarland/</guid>
      <description>This study examined stereotype threat in a simulated selection exercise so that stereotype threat and face validity both could be manipulated. Black and White college undergraduates completed a test to &amp;ldquo;understand how to select people for retail managerial positions&amp;rdquo; and that the top 15% of performers would receive $20. Before beginning the test, students were told that it was diagnostic of intelligence (stereotype threat for Blacks), a good indicator of &amp;ldquo;skills as a retail manager&amp;rdquo; (non-diagnostic), or that the test was difficult (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pronin, Steele, &amp; Ross, 2004</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/pronin_steele_ross/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/pronin_steele_ross/</guid>
      <description>This paper reports three studies exploring women&amp;rsquo;s bifurcation of feminine identity - disidentification with aspects of one&amp;rsquo;s social identity linked with disparagement in a domain - in response to stereotype threat experienced in mathematics. Bifurcation was theorized as a mechanism by which women might resolve the tension between their gender identity and their identification with a given domain when poor performance might be expected based on their gender. Results confirmed that women alter their self-descriptions in response to stereotype threat.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quinn &amp; Spencer, 2001</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/quinn_spencer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/quinn_spencer/</guid>
      <description>This paper reports the results from two studies examining the effects of stereotype threat on problem solving, focusing on the stereotype of male superiority in mathematical ability. Experiment 1 focused on the performance of male and female students on mathematical word problems. When problems were presented in a verbal format, males outperformed females. When the word problems were presented in their basic numeric form, however, performance was equivalent. In Experiment 2, male and female students attempted to solve the same difficult math problems but did so either in standard conditions (where there exists a stereotype of male superiority in math) or a control condition where, participants were told, &amp;ldquo;men and women perform equally well on these problems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quinn, Kahng, &amp; Crocker, 2004</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/quinn_kahng_crocker/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/quinn_kahng_crocker/</guid>
      <description>Three experiments examined how revealing hidden a stigmatizing condition to others can affect task performance. In Experiment 1, participants were undergraduates who either had or had not previously received treatment for a mental illness. All students completed a test based on the Analytic portion of the GRE. Before starting the test, however, half of the students were asked questions designed to reveal their mental health history and were told that the test was diagnostic of their ability (stereotype threat for individuals with a history of mental illness) or did not answer such questions and were told that the test was not diagnostic of ability (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rahhal, Hasher, &amp; Colcombe, 2001</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/rahhal_hasher_colcombe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/rahhal_hasher_colcombe/</guid>
      <description>These studies examined the role of stereotype threat in accounting for memory deficits in older adults. In two experiments, younger (average age = 19.5 &amp;amp; 19.3 years, respectively) and older participants (average age = 69.4 years, range = 61-75 &amp;amp; 67.8, 60-74, respectively) completed a memory task under instructions that either emphasized (e.g., &amp;ldquo;we are interested in how good your memory is&amp;rdquo;) or de-emphasized (e.g., &amp;ldquo;we are interested in your ability to learn facts&amp;rdquo;) that memory was being assessed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roberson, Deitch, Brief, &amp; Block, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/roberson_deitch_brief_block/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/roberson_deitch_brief_block/</guid>
      <description>This correlational study examined stereotype threat in workplace settings, focusing on the impact of solo status. A total of 166 African-American members of an association for African-American professionals in utility industries responded to a survey on work experiences and attitudes. Individuals who were the sole minority in their department reported experiencing a greater degree of stereotype threat in the work environment. In addition, stereotype threat affected feedback monitoring such that individuals experiencing higher degrees of stereotype threat were more likely to compare themselves with peers, to observe what behaviors are rewarded to modify their own performance, to notice how they were treated by their manager and the characteristics of people who are rewarded by their manager, and to pay attention to interactions with peers, feedback from others, and casual remarks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rosenthal &amp; Crisp, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/rosenthal_crisp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/rosenthal_crisp/</guid>
      <description>Three studies examined whether blurring intergroup boundaries might attenuate stereotype threat. In Experiment 1, women undergraduates were asked either &amp;ldquo;to think of five things that men and women can have in common (i.e., characteristics that men and women share)&amp;rdquo; (category overlap) or did not complete this task (control) before completing the main dependent measure. The dependent variable involved individuals indicating their interest in pursuing eight different careers, four of which pilot tests showed were strongly (mechanical engineer, military officer) or weakly (dentist, accountant) stereotypical for men and four of which were strongly (registered nurse, primary school teacher) or weakly (physical therapist, social worker) stereotypical for women.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rosenthal, Crisp, &amp; Suen, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/rosenthal_crisp_suen/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/rosenthal_crisp_suen/</guid>
      <description>Two experiments tested whether emphasizing similarities between groups might reduce the harm of stereotype threat by changing performance expectancies. In Experiment 1, male and female university students were asked to generate similarities between men&amp;rsquo;s and women&amp;rsquo;s physical attributes, academic characteristics, or non-academic characteristics or were not asked to generate any similarities (control). Students were then asked to imagine that they were the only (man/woman) in a class of eight other (women/men) and that they had to take a (Math vs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>McFarland, Lev-Arey, &amp; Ziegert, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/mcfarland_lev-arey_ziegert/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/mcfarland_lev-arey_ziegert/</guid>
      <description>This study examined whether stereotype threat might be less likely in situations where there are incentives for strong performance. In addition, the study was designed to determine if stereotype threat might also affect performance on a test irrelevant to the domain in question. To address these issues, Black and White undergraduates were told that the study examined performance on two different types of tests and that high performers across both tests would receive a monetary reward.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>McGlone &amp; Aronson, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/mcglone_aronson/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/mcglone_aronson/</guid>
      <description>This experiment examines how highlighting different social identities can moderate vulnerability to stereotype threat. Male and female undergraduates completed the the Vandenberg Mental Rotation Test (VMRT), a standard test of visual–spatial ability. Before taking the test, students completed questionnaires designed to highlight different aspects of their social identities that should differentially be associated with stereotypical gender differences in spatial abilities. One questionnaire highlighted gender identity, containing items that made reference to students&amp;rsquo; sex or gender (stereotype threat for women).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>McIntyre, Lord, Gresky, Ten Eyck, Frye, &amp; Bond Jr., 2005</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/mcintyre_lord_gresky_teneyck_frye_bond/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/mcintyre_lord_gresky_teneyck_frye_bond/</guid>
      <description>This study examined the relation between exposure to positive role models and reduction of performance decrements under stereotype threat. Men and women college undergraduates were asked to participate in two studies, one focusing on &amp;ldquo;developing stimulus materials for future experiments&amp;rdquo; and one involving finding solutions to math problems. In introducing the tasks, the experimenter always mentioned that &amp;ldquo;women perform worse than men on math tests.&amp;rdquo; The first task actually allowed some students to read essays describing women who were successful in various fields (a woman architect, lawyer, doctor, or inventor), and students read 0, 1, 2, 3, or 4 essays about successful women.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>McIntyre, Paulson, &amp; Lord, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/mcintyre_paulson_lord/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/mcintyre_paulson_lord/</guid>
      <description>Two experiments assessed whether exposing women to other women&amp;rsquo;s accomplishments might alleviate stereotype threat effects. In Experiment 1, male and female undergraduates were told by a female experimenter that they would be assisting in developing new items for the GRE Quantitative test. The experiment mentioned, &amp;ldquo;some research shows men outperform women in mathematics, but the empirical evidence is mixed.&amp;rdquo; Students were also told that they could complete some additional experiments for extra credit later in the semester, but students were told either that only women could participate in these additional studies because &amp;ldquo;women produce more reliable and valid data, comprehend the task requirements better, and produce better results in all types of psychological experiments&amp;rdquo; (women superior) or were told nothing about restrictions on extra credit based on gender (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>McKay, Doverspike, Bowen-Hilton, &amp; Martin, 2002</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/mckay_doverspike_bowen-hilton_martin/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/mckay_doverspike_bowen-hilton_martin/</guid>
      <description>This study assessed the impact of stereotype threat on performance on Raven&amp;rsquo;s Advanced Progressive Matrices (APM) task, a non-verbal test of cognitive ability. White and Black students at both a predominately White and historically Black college completed a biographical form and then the APM after being told either that it was a &amp;ldquo;test diagnostic of intellectual ability&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for Blacks) or a &amp;ldquo;test of pattern completion skill&amp;rdquo; and that &amp;ldquo;ability would not be measured using the test&amp;rdquo; (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>McKay, Doverspike, Bowen-Hilton, &amp; McKay, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/mckay_doverspike_bowen-hilton_mckay/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/mckay_doverspike_bowen-hilton_mckay/</guid>
      <description>This study examined whether demographic variables and stereotype threat might account for performance deficits on the Raven Advanced Progressive Matrices (APM) task, a non-verbal test of cognitive ability. White and Black undergraduates completed the APM after being told either that it was diagnostic (stereotype threat for Blacks) or non-diagnostic (control) of intellectual ability. Black students reported feeling more stereotype threat and their performance was negatively affected in the former condition. Feelings of stereotype threat appeared to partially mediate the relation between task framing and performance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>McKown &amp; Weinstein, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/mckown_weinstein/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/mckown_weinstein/</guid>
      <description>These studies examined the development of stereotype awareness and stereotype threat in children. As children become aware that other individuals might believe in and use stereotypes, susceptibility to stereotype threat might increase. In Experiment 1, children ranging from under seven to over ten years of age with stigmatized (African-American, Latino, Native American) and nonstigmatized (White, Asian-American) ethnic identities completed one task requiring them to infer another person&amp;rsquo;s stereotype and a second task to assess awareness of widely held cultural stereotypes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Murphy, Steele, &amp; Gross, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/murphy_steele_gross/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/murphy_steele_gross/</guid>
      <description>This experiment examined how contextual cues can induce stereotype threat and reduce one&amp;rsquo;s sense of belonging. Male and female undergraduates who were majoring in math, science, and engineering were asked to view a videotape of a discussion that supposedly took place at a conference on leadership in the sciences to assess whether the conference should be hosted by the local university in the future. The gender composition of the discussants was varied so that either 75% of the discussants were males (reflecting approximate sex differences in obtaining degrees in these fields in the U.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Muzzatti &amp; Agnoli, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/muzzatti_agnoli/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/muzzatti_agnoli/</guid>
      <description>Two experiments examined the development of attitudes about mathematics in children and vulnerability to stereotype threat. In Experiment 1, Italian boys and girls in grades 2-5 (approximately 6-11 years of age) answered questions designed to assess their beliefs and opinions about mathematics. Approximately two weeks later, the children completed a math test after reading vignettes either about 9 famous male and 1 famous female mathematician (stereotype threat for girls) or vignettes about 10 neutral stimuli (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Neuville &amp; Croizet, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/neuville_croizet/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/neuville_croizet/</guid>
      <description>This experiment examined whether stereotype threat effects would emerge in a real classroom setting. To see if they would, French children in the 3rd grade (7-8 years of age) were asked to color drawings of a boy or a girl with a ball, respectively (to highlight self-gender) or a landscape (control) then to complete a set of difficult and easy math problems. Results showed that girls performed less well on the difficult items when their gender had been highlighted compared to the control condition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nguyen &amp; Ryan, 2008</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/nguyen_ryan/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/nguyen_ryan/</guid>
      <description>This paper reports a meta-analysis (a statistical examination of data from multiple studies) assessing the impact of stereotype threat on test performance in minorities and women. Although the meta-analysis showed that both minorities and women were susceptible to stereotype threat, decrements in performance on difficult tests were larger for minorities than for women. For minorities, stereotype threat effects were largest when cues signaling stereotype threat were moderately explicit; women performed most poorly when gender was subtly highlighted.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nguyen, O&#39;Neal, &amp; Ryan, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/nguyen_oneal_ryan/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/nguyen_oneal_ryan/</guid>
      <description>This experiment explored the possible mediating roles of cognition, motivation, and emotionality in performance on a cognitive ability test collected under the guise of a job application exercise. Black and White college undergraduates participated in a study that was supposedly &amp;ldquo;to examine the extent to which perceived job desirability would influence job applicants’ selection test performance.&amp;rdquo; A monetary award was promised for excellent performance. All participants also completed a demographic questionnaire indicating their gender, age, year in college, major, cumulative GPA, and ACT or SAT scores.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nussbaum &amp; Steele, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/nussbaum_steele/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/nussbaum_steele/</guid>
      <description>This experiment examined the possibility that short-term disengagement arising from stereotype threat, at least in some contexts, might allow increased motivation and persistence. If individuals under stereotype threat distance themselves from a task to reduce the implications of task performance for self-evaluation, motivation might not be undermined. This study tested for this temporary defensive response by having White and Black students complete a difficult anagram task that was described as &amp;ldquo;not a diagnostic test [but] an activity we use as a warm-up for problem solving exercises&amp;rdquo; (no threat) or as &amp;ldquo;diagnostic of academic ability, much like other similar tests such as the GRE, the MCAT, or the LSAT&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for Black students).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>O&#39;Brien &amp; Crandall, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/obrien_crandall/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/obrien_crandall/</guid>
      <description>This experiment tested whether performance on tasks under stereotype threat mirror the effects of arousal demonstrated in other domains. Specifically, it has been shown that arousal tends to decrease performance on difficult tasks but to increase performance on simple tasks. Male and female students were told they would complete a series of math tests that either have shown gender differences (stereotype threat for women) or have not shown gender differences (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kray, Reb, Galinsky, &amp; Thompson, 2004</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/kray_reb_galinsky_thompson/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/kray_reb_galinsky_thompson/</guid>
      <description>Two experiments examined conditions under which stereotype threat might produce reactance, behavior in opposition to stereotype threat. In Experiment 1, male-female negotiation dyads were given either a strong or weak gender stereotype manipulation implying male superiority in negotiating. One of the negotiation partners was provided with social power by suggesting that they could leave the negotiation and still receive a good settlement, and the individual with high power was female in half the dyads and male in the other half of dyads.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kray, Thompson, &amp; Galinsky, 2001</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/kray_thompson_galinsky/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/kray_thompson_galinsky/</guid>
      <description>These experiments assess the impact of gender-stereotype activation on performance expectations in negotiation situations, a domain in which gender stereotypes favor men. In Experiment 1, MBA students formed male-female dyadic pairs to conduct a negotiation over the purchase of a biotechnology plant. Half of the negotiation teams were told that the negotiation task was extremely diagnostic of negotiating ability (stereotype threat for women) and half were told the task was not an accurate gauge of negotiating ability (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lesko &amp; Corpus, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/lesko_corpus/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/lesko_corpus/</guid>
      <description>In this experiment, men and women who varied in their level of math identity completed a difficult math test either under stereotype threat (where participants were told that males and females perform differently on the test) or no stereotype threat (where participants were told there are no gender differences in test performance). After controlling for self-reported math SAT scores, a typical stereotype threat effect emerged; women performed more poorly under stereotype threat than when not under stereotype threat, but men showed no difference in performance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Levy, 1996</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/levy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/levy/</guid>
      <description>Two studies examined the effects of elderly stereotype activation on memory performance. In Experiment 1, men and women 60 years of age and older (average age = 73) volunteered for a study on memory improvement. All participants completed an exercise that involved the subliminal presentation of stimuli to activate either negative (e.g., decline, dependent) or positive (e.g., wise, enlightened) stereotypes of the elderly. Individuals then were randomly assigned to receive an explicit external attribution for success in the upcoming memory task (that light exposure will help their memory), an explicit internal attribution for success (that they were in a placebo condition so their memory success will be due to their effort) or no feedback.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leyens, Desert, Croizet, &amp; Darcis, 2000</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/leyens_desert_croizet_darcis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/leyens_desert_croizet_darcis/</guid>
      <description>This experiment was one of the first studies to examine stereotype threat in groups that are not traditionally stigmatized. If stereotype threat could be established in traditionally non-stigmatized groups, it would suggest that stereotype threat is a general phenomenon that could potentially affect anyone in contexts where expectations of low performance are invoked. Female and male undergraduates completed three tasks that had been presented as an exercise to &amp;ldquo;better understanding the cognitive factors involved in the processing of verbal information&amp;rdquo; (control) or as a way to understand gender differences in processing affective information with the reminder that &amp;ldquo;men are not as apt as women to deal with affect in general and specifically to process affective information as effectively&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for men).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Major, Spencer, Schmader, Wolfe, &amp; Crocker, 1998</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/major_spencer_schmader_wolfe_crocker/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/major_spencer_schmader_wolfe_crocker/</guid>
      <description>Two experiments tested the notion that stereotype threat can produce disengagement from domains implicated by stereotype threat. In Experiment 1, Black and White undergraduates were told they were to take a test that either &amp;ldquo;may be biased against people belonging to certain ethnic and/or racial groups&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for Blacks) or &amp;ldquo;is culturally unbiased&amp;hellip;the scores are a true test of intelligence, regardless of ethnic background&amp;rdquo; (control). The students then completed either an easy or a difficult task involving word associations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Martens, Johns, Greenberg, &amp; Schimel, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/martens_johns_greenberg_schimel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/martens_johns_greenberg_schimel/</guid>
      <description>Two studies examine the consequences of self-affirmation on women operating under stereotype threat. In Experiment 1, male and female undergraduates who had a history of strong math performance completed a challenging math test. Before doing so, students were told that the test was being administered to give the researchers a sense of &amp;ldquo;people&amp;rsquo;s impressions of the problems&amp;rdquo; (control) or that the test measured &amp;ldquo;math and reasoning abilities&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for women).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marx &amp; Goff, 2005</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/marx_goff/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/marx_goff/</guid>
      <description>This study examined the consequences of stereotype threat on test performance when the test administrator was of same or a different race. Black and White undergraduates highly identified with their verbal ability completed a challenging verbal test under conditions that typically produce stereotype threat. Specifically, the test was described as diagnostic, and students were asked to indicate their race on the test booklet before beginning the test. The test administrator was either Black or White, and the administrator&amp;rsquo;s competence in the verbal domain was established through several means.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marx &amp; Roman, 2002</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/marx_roman/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/marx_roman/</guid>
      <description>This paper reports three experiments examining the attenuation of stereotype threat when women are provided with role models who suggest suggest competence. Experiment 1 involved highly math-identified male and female students who were given a difficult, diagnostic math test by one of three male or female experimenters. The math competence of the experimenter was established by indicating that the experimenter had developed the test and would be providing feedback on the students performance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marx &amp; Stapel, 2006a</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/marx_stapel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/marx_stapel/</guid>
      <description>This study investigated the role of emotional responses in reaction to stereotype threat. Various emotions were measured both before and after individuals took a test under either the presence or absence of stereotype threat. For those students operating under stereotype threat, heightened anxiety was experienced before taking the test and heightened frustration occurred after the test was concluded. Frustration correlated negatively with performance in the threat condition, such that higher levels of frustration were associated with poorer test performance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marx &amp; Stapel, 2006b</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/marx_stapel_2006b/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/marx_stapel_2006b/</guid>
      <description>These studies showed the different consequences of group priming (highlighting a social category) and stereotype threat (highlighting a social identity). Whereas group priming tends to affect behavior in a stereotype-consistent fashion, stereotype threat appears to affect only individuals whose social identities are tied to the stereotype. According to this view, the relevance of the stereotype to the self is necessary for stereotype threat. Highlighting any stereotype can produce stereotype-consistent behavior, but the stereotype must be self-relevant to create stereotype threat.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marx, Ko, &amp; Friedman, In Press</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/marx_ko_friedman/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/marx_ko_friedman/</guid>
      <description>This study used a large national sample to investigate the impact of Barack Obama&amp;rsquo;s campaign and election on racial differences in test performance under stereotype threat. Samples of Black and White adults who had volunteered to complete a series of web-based experiments were contacted at four points during 2008: i) just prior to the Democratic National Convention (Aug 22-24), ii) in the days following Obama&amp;rsquo;s nomination acceptance speech (Aug 28-Sept 2), iii) midway between the convention and the general election (Oct 1-4), and iv) in the days following Obama&amp;rsquo;s election (Nov 5-7).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Marx, Stapel, &amp; Muller, 2005</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/marx_stapel_muller/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/marx_stapel_muller/</guid>
      <description>This article examines the role of collective identity (i.e., when thoughts about one&amp;rsquo;s social groups are prominent in one&amp;rsquo;s thoughts) in stereotype threat. It was reasoned that if stereotype threat affects performance by increasing the prominence or accessibility of a group-based stereotype, then the accessibility of stereotype-relevant group memberships should be higher in settings in which a stereotype might apply than in situations in which it could not. Experiment 1 tested this notion by leading male and female undergraduates to expect that they would complete a math test that was described either as &amp;ldquo;diagnostic of math ability&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for women) or as a &amp;ldquo;reasoning exercise&amp;rdquo; (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mayer &amp; Hanges, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/mayer_hanges/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/mayer_hanges/</guid>
      <description>This paper builds on previous work (McKay, Doverspike, Bowen-Hilton, &amp;amp; Martin, 2002) examining the effects of stereotype threat on performance on Raven&amp;rsquo;s Advanced Progressive Matrices (APM) task, a non-verbal task that has been described as &amp;ldquo;culture-reduced&amp;rdquo; and a relatively &amp;ldquo;pure&amp;rdquo; measure of cognitive ability and reasoning. In this experiment, Black and White undergraduates were told they would take a test frequently used in professional personnel selection. The test was actually the APM, which was described either as assessing intelligence (stereotype threat for Blacks) or perceptual ability (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Johns, Schmader, &amp; Martens, 2005</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/johns_schmader_martens/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/johns_schmader_martens/</guid>
      <description>This paper reports a study examining whether informing women about stereotype threat can improve performance on a test that would ordinarily provoke stereotype threat. Male and female college students completed a set of difficult math problems that were described either as a problem-solving task or as a math test. In a third condition, the task was described as a math test but students also were briefly told about stereotype threat and that it could negatively affect women&amp;rsquo;s performance on the test.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Josephs, Newman, Brown, &amp; Beer, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/josephs_newman_brown_beer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/josephs_newman_brown_beer/</guid>
      <description>Stereotype threat can be conceptualized as a situation involving the potential loss of status for a group member. Given that baseline testosterone levels have been shown to be related to status-relevant concerns and behavior in both humans and other animals, it was hypothesized that individual differences in baseline testosterone might moderate stereotype threat effects. In Experiment 1, highly math-identified male and female undergraduates completed a math test after answering questions that focused on gender stereotypes in math (stereotype threat for women) or coming to college (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keller &amp; Dauenheimer, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/keller_dauenheimer/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/keller_dauenheimer/</guid>
      <description>This study examined emotional responses following performance on a math task as a function of stereotype threat. Male and female German high school students completed a difficult math task under one of two conditions. Whereas half of the students were told that the task tends to produce gender differences with men outperforming women (stereotype threat for women), the other half were told that there were no gender differences on the task (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keller, 2002</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/keller/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/keller/</guid>
      <description>This study examined performance on and responses to a math task as a function of stereotype threat. Male and female German high school students who took math as a regular subject were asked to complete a difficult math task under one of two conditions. Half of the students were told that the task tended to produce gender differences with men outperforming women (stereotype threat for girls). The other half of the students were told nothing about gender differences on the task (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keller, 2007(b)</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/keller_2007b/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/keller_2007b/</guid>
      <description>This experiment used predictions derived from Regulatory Focus Theory (Higgins, 1998) to examine performance under stereotype threat. Regulatory Focus Theory posits the co-existence of two systems involved in self-regulation. Whereas the promotion system is concerned about gain/non-gain and strives to achieve desired endstates, the prevention system focuses on loss/non-loss and strives to avoid undesired endstates. If stereotype threat involves the fear of confirming undesired stereotypes, then stereotype threat should have particularly detrimental effects on performance when the prevention system is activated and produce more modest effects under a promotion focus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keller, 2007a</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/keller_2007a/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/keller_2007a/</guid>
      <description>This study involved a manipulation of stereotype threat, measures of domain identification, and test items of varying difficulty. Although these factors have been examined in separate settings, this study examined the effects of all three variables within a single design and in a realistic school setting. Male and female German secondary school students who took math as a regular subject were asked to complete a difficult math task under one of two conditions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kellow &amp; Jones, 2005</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/kellow_jones_2005/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/kellow_jones_2005/</guid>
      <description>This study examined stereotype threat effects among 9th-grade African-American and White students who participated in a group testing session on &amp;ldquo;mathematical reasoning.&amp;rdquo; Students completed the APR Spatial Ability Test that had been described either as predictive of performance on standardized tests in mathematics (stereotype threat) or where students had been reassured that the test was unbiased and culturally fair (no stereotype threat). Results showed performance on the APR (controlling for previous test performance) did not differ significantly between African-American and White students when the test was described as unbiased.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kellow &amp; Jones, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/kellow_jones_2007/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/kellow_jones_2007/</guid>
      <description>Following the procedures of Kellow and Jones (2005), this experiment examined stereotype threat effects among 9th-grade African-American and White students who participated in a group testing session on &amp;ldquo;mathematical reasoning.&amp;rdquo; Students completed the APR Spatial Ability Test that had been described either as predictive of performance on standardized tests in mathematics (stereotype threat for Blacks) or where students had been reassured that the test was unbiased and culturally fair (no stereotype threat).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kiefer &amp; Sekaquaptewa, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/kiefer_sekaquaptewa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/kiefer_sekaquaptewa/</guid>
      <description>This study examined the moderating role of implicit stereotype endorsement on stereotype threat. In the experiment, female undergraduates completed a math test that was described as either diagnostic (stereotype threat) or nondiagnostic (control) of mathematical ability. After finishing the task, they completed implicit measures (see Greenwald et al., 1998) of gender stereotyping (i.e., stronger male-math than female-math associations), gender identification (i.e., stronger self-female than self-male associations), and math identification (i.e., stronger self-math than other-math associations), and an explicit measure of math-gender stereotyping.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Klein, Pohl, &amp; Ndagijimana, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/klein_pohl_ndagijimana/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/klein_pohl_ndagijimana/</guid>
      <description>This experiment focused on stereotype threat amongst residents of Belgium with sub-Saharan African origins in the context of a job interview setting. African adults who had lived in Belgium at least 5 years were recruited to complete a relatively culturally-unbiased test commonly used in job selection. The description of the test provided by an African experimenter was varied between conditions. Individuals were told that &amp;ldquo;compared to Belgians, very few Africans have performed well on it&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat), that &amp;ldquo;the number of Africans who have performed well on this test exceeds the number of Belgians&amp;rdquo; (stereotype lift), or that &amp;ldquo;there are as many Africans as Belgians who have performed well on this test&amp;rdquo; (no difference).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Koch, Müller, &amp; Sieverding, 2008</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/koch_muller_sieverding/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/koch_muller_sieverding/</guid>
      <description>This experiment examines the influence of stereotype threat on attributions for failure involving women&amp;rsquo;s performance on a computer-based task. Male and female college students were asked to find a document on the internet and to save it to a memory stick. Before doing so, they were informed that &amp;ldquo;women have previously performed worse than men have in this task&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for women), that &amp;ldquo;women have previously performed better than men have in this task&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for men), or were given no information about gender differences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Koenig &amp; Eagly, 2005</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/koenig_eagly/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/koenig_eagly/</guid>
      <description>This study assessed whether men are susceptible to stereotype threat regarding social sensitivity. Men and women undergraduates completed a test after it was described as measuring either &amp;ldquo;social sensitivity&amp;rdquo; on which &amp;ldquo;men do worse than women&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for men) or &amp;ldquo;complex information processing&amp;rdquo; (control). The test was actually the Interpersonal Perception Task (IPT-15; Costanzo &amp;amp; Archer, 1993) that assesses individuals&amp;rsquo; accuracy in interpreting others&amp;rsquo; expressive behavior. Men performed more poorly on the task in the stereotype threat compared with the control condition, but women did not differ in their performance between conditions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kray, Galinsky, &amp; Thompson, 2002</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/kray_galinsky_thompson/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/kray_galinsky_thompson/</guid>
      <description>Two experiments examine the role of masculine and feminine traits in performance of women and men in negotiation situations. In Experiment 1, male-female dyads of MBA students were told that an upcoming negotiation exercise was highly diagnostic of negotiating ability. In addition, participants were told either that excellent verbal skills, listening skills, and insight into other&amp;rsquo;s feelings assist in negotiation (female stereotype benefit condition) or that well-prepared, humorous, open-minded individuals do well in negotiations (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Krendl, Richeson, Kelley, &amp; Heatherton, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/krendl_richeson_kelley_heatherton/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/krendl_richeson_kelley_heatherton/</guid>
      <description>This experiment used functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) to investigate the brain regions engaged as women performed math in the absence and presence of stereotype threat. Female undergraduates who highly identified with math completed a series of math problems while in an fMRI scanner (to establish baseline levels of brain activity) then completed a task to assess attitudes towards math because &amp;ldquo;research has shown gender differences in math ability and performance&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat) or to assess political attitudes (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gonzales, Blanton, &amp; Williams, 2002</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/gonzales_blanton_williams/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/gonzales_blanton_williams/</guid>
      <description>Stereotype threat can occur based on any social identity where there exists a stereotype of poor performance. This paper addresses the risk of stereotype threat based on both gender and ethnicity experienced by Latina women. In this experiment, White and Latino/a undergraduates were asked to complete a difficult test measuring mathematical and analytical ability. Half the participants were told that the test was a good indicator of their &amp;ldquo;actual abilities and limitations&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for Latinas) whereas the other half heard no mention about ability (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good, Aronson, &amp; Harder, 2008</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/good_aronson_harder/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/good_aronson_harder/</guid>
      <description>This field experiment explored stereotype threat and its negation in high-level college math courses that typically serve as gateway courses for careers in math and science. Male and female students in the last course of an advanced university calculus sequence were given a practice test containing items similar to the GRE. All students were told that the test was &amp;ldquo;aimed at measuring your mathematical abilities&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat) but half of the students additionally were assured that &amp;ldquo;this mathematics test has not shown any gender differences in performance or mathematics ability&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat negation).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good, Aronson, &amp; Inzlicht, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/good_aronson_inzlicht/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/good_aronson_inzlicht/</guid>
      <description>This paper reports the results of interventions designed to improve performance of junior high students on standardized tests using techniques that have been show to increase enjoyment, valuing of education, and grades in other studies (Aronson, Fried, &amp;amp; Good, 2002; Wilson &amp;amp; Linville, 1985). Seventh grade students received a college-aged mentor for a full academic year with whom they discussed adjusting to a new school environment and effective strategies for studying.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gresky, Ten Eyck, Lord, &amp; McIntyre, 2005</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/gresky_tendyck_lord_mcintyre/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/gresky_tendyck_lord_mcintyre/</guid>
      <description>This experiment examined the role of multiple identities in attenuating stereotype threat. Male and female undergraduates who varied in their level of identification with math were asked to answer some questions that supposedly were to be used in a new version of the GRE math test. To induce stereotype threat, researchers told the students that the test was being used &amp;ldquo;because of the well-known stereotype that men usually outperform women on math tests&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for women).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gupta &amp; Bhawe, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/gupta_bhawe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/gupta_bhawe/</guid>
      <description>This experiment examined the impact of proactive personality — the tendency to take action to change one&amp;rsquo;s circumstances — and stereotype threat on women&amp;rsquo;s aspirations in entrepreneurial fields. Given that characteristics stereotypically assumed to produce entrepreneurial success are masculine in nature, it was hypothesized that exposing women to these stereotypes might reduce their expressed interest in pursuing a career in business. To test this hypothesis, women enrolled in a university business program read an article about entrepreneurship.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Harrison, Stevens, Monty, &amp; Coakley, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/harrison_stevens_monty_coakley/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/harrison_stevens_monty_coakley/</guid>
      <description>This experiment builds on research showing stereotype threat based on social class (Croizet &amp;amp; Claire, 1998). Similar to Croizet &amp;amp; Claire (1998), students who were low and high in SES participated in the study. Unlike Croizet &amp;amp; Claire, middle-class students were also included, and both White and minority students were included in the sample. Students completed a difficult math and verbal test with instructions suggesting that the test provided a &amp;ldquo;valid assessment of their abilities&amp;rdquo; and that &amp;ldquo;middle and upper income students consistently performed better than lower income students on standardized tests&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for low SES) or that the &amp;ldquo;purpose of the research is to understand the psychological factors involved in completing standardized tests&amp;rdquo; (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hess &amp; Hinson, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/hess_hinson/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/hess_hinson/</guid>
      <description>This study examines how age and stereotype threat interact to affect memory performance. Adults between the ages of 24 to 86 were recruited from a community to participate in the study. Before completing a test of memory, individuals read newspaper-type reports that either reinforced the inevitability of memory decrements with old age or negated the inevitability of stereotypical decrements. Participants then were allowed to study a list of 30 words for two minutes and later wrote down all the words they could recall.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hess, Auman, Colcombe, &amp; Rahhal, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/hess_auman_colcombe_rahhal/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/hess_auman_colcombe_rahhal/</guid>
      <description>In this experiment, older (average age = 70.8 years, range = 62-84) and younger (19.3, 18-30) adults completed an questionnaire assessing the degree that they valued their memory ability. Individuals then read newspaper-type reports that either reinforced the inevitability of memory decrements with old age (e.g. &amp;ldquo;to maintain adequate levels of functioning, older adults may have to increasingly depend upon the help of memory tools as well as friends and family&amp;rdquo;) or negated the inevitability of stereotypical decrements (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Huguet &amp; Régner, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/huguet_regner/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/huguet_regner/</guid>
      <description>Two experiments examined whether school children are influenced by stereotype threat in regular classroom environments. In Experiment 1, highly math-identified boys and girls between 11-13 years in age were presented with a version of the Rey-Osterrieth Complex Figure (ROCF) recall memory task, an exercise believed to tap a variety of skills essential for successful academic performance. Half the students were told that the task was a &amp;ldquo;geometry test&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for girls) and the other students were told it was a &amp;ldquo;memory game&amp;rdquo; (no stereotype threat).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inzlicht &amp; Ben-Zeev, 2000</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/inzlicht_ben-zeev/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/inzlicht_ben-zeev/</guid>
      <description>This paper presents two experiments in which the gender composition of groups of college students was varied to examine its impact on performance of women on math and verbal tests. In Experiment 1, women completed difficult items from either the math or verbal portion of the GRE in a room along with either two male or female accomplices of the experimenter who posed as fellow test-takers. The women had been led to believe that their scores would be shared at the end of the testing session.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inzlicht &amp; Ben-Zeev, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/inzlicht_ben-zeev_2003/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/inzlicht_ben-zeev_2003/</guid>
      <description>This experiment involved highly math-identified women who completed a difficult math test in a room either with two females or two male accomplices of the experimenter who posed as fellow test-takers. Half the women were led to believe that their scores would be shared at the end of the testing session, and half were told that their scores would be anonymous both to the fellow students and the experimenter. Analyses of the math scores showed that women performed more poorly in the presence of the males, and this was true regardless of whether the scores were private or were to be shared.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inzlicht, Aronson, Good, &amp; McKay, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/inzlicht_aronson_good_mckay/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/inzlicht_aronson_good_mckay/</guid>
      <description>This paper examines whether differences in self-monitoring (i.e., the ability to regulate one’s expressions to cultivate a desired public image) might moderate stereotype threat effects. Individuals high in self-monitoring were expected to show fewer performance decrements under numerical-minority status (a condition that typically creates stereotype threat) because their habitual and well-practiced impression-management strategies reduce the threat imposed by situations involving potential stereotype confirmation. Experiment 1 tested this hypothesis by having math-identified female undergraduates complete a difficult math test either in the presence of one female and two males (minority status) or three females (same-sex).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inzlicht, McKay, &amp; Aronson, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/inzlicht_mckay_aronson/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/inzlicht_mckay_aronson/</guid>
      <description>This paper examines whether being associated with stigma might reduce one&amp;rsquo;s ability to control attention and behavior. If self-control is a limited resource, then coping with anxious feelings and activated stereotypes, and avoiding stereotype-confirmation under stereotype threat might reduce the resources available to effectively regulate behavior in other unrelated contexts. Three experiments were conducted to test these hypotheses. In Experiment 1, African-American undergraduates completed measures designed to assess their anxious expectations of being victims of prejudice and their estimates of successful regulation of academic-relevant behavior.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jamieson &amp; Harkins, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/jamieson_harkins/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/jamieson_harkins/</guid>
      <description>This paper reports four experiments testing the notion that one consequence of stereotype threat is increased motivation to perform well. Increased motivation to perform should facilitate the dominant response on a given task, and dominant responses, if correct, should improve task performance. If the dominant response is incorrect, however, then performance should be harmed under greater motivation. To test these hypotheses, students completed a visual attention task (an antisaccade task) in which an individual must inhibit the tendency to look at an irrelevant, peripheral stimulus while directing vision to determine the orientation of a target stimulus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Johns, Inzlicht, &amp; Schmader, 2008</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/johns_inzlicht_schmader/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/johns_inzlicht_schmader/</guid>
      <description>This paper examines the role of emotion regulation in stereotype threat. It is proposed that stereotype threat provokes a variety of emotional responses. To regulate (i.e., control) these emotional responses requires working memory resources, depriving the individual under threat of the cognitive resources needed for optimal task performance. These ideas were pursued across four experiments. In Experiment 1, female undergraduates were asked to perform a task measuring mathematical aptitude in the presence of two men (stereotype threat) or reflective of problem solving skills in the presence of two other women (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Croizet, Després, Gauzins, Huguet, Leyens, &amp; Méot, 2004</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/croizet_depres_gauzins_huguet_leyens_meot/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/croizet_depres_gauzins_huguet_leyens_meot/</guid>
      <description>This experiment used a physiological measure reflective of cognitive demand, heart rate variability (HRV), to examine performance disruption under stereotype threat. Both Science and Psychology majors in France (for which there are stereotypes suggesting higher intelligence among the former) were asked to complete a test that was described either as a valid measure of general intellectual ability (stereotype threat for Psychology majors) or as nondiagnostic of ability (control). An electrocardiogram measured HRV while students took the test.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cullen, Hardison, &amp; Sackett, 2004</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cullen_hardison_sackett/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cullen_hardison_sackett/</guid>
      <description>Analyses of two large data sets collected in real-world settings were used to test predictions derived from theorizing on stereotype threat. Specifically, the notions that stereotype threat should emerge only among those highly identified with a domain and only with tests that push the limits of individuals’ abilities was used to develop hypothesized models of the relation between testing and performance on a criterion. Both assumptions suggest that the test-performance relationship should be nonlinear for members of minority groups and that prediction of performance for minorities should be poorest at the highest levels of test performance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cullen, Waters, &amp; Sackett, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cullen_waters_sackett/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cullen_waters_sackett/</guid>
      <description>This study followed on a previous study, Cullen, Hardison, and Sackett (2004), that questioned whether stereotype threat effects emerge in real-world testing contexts. That work showed there was little support for the prediction that stereotype threat emerges only among those highly identified with a domain. Specifically, under the assumption that domain identification would be highest for those individuals at the upper end of the performance distribution, it was predicted that regression lines characterizing the test-performance relation would be non-linear for minorities but linear for Whites.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Danaher &amp; Crandall, 2008</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/danaher_crandall/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/danaher_crandall/</guid>
      <description>This paper offers a re-analysis of data collected and presented by Stricker &amp;amp; Ward (2004), in which the claim was made that there were no &amp;ldquo;effects of inquiring about ethnicity and gender on performance on [standardized] tests&amp;rdquo; (p. 685). The current authors critique the use of conservative decision criteria used in the original analyses. Specifically, Stricker and Ward (2004) only considered results to be significant if p&amp;lt;.05 in the overall ANOVA, p&amp;lt;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dar-Nimrod &amp; Heine, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/dar-nimrod_heine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/dar-nimrod_heine/</guid>
      <description>This paper reports two studies examining the impact of attributions for gender differences in math on math performance. In Experiment 1, men and women completed a math test, then a reading comprehension test, and a second math test. The content of the reading comprehension essay served as the experimental manipulation. Two essays acknowledged gender differences in math performance but they attributed those differences either to genetic or experiential causes. A third essay denied gender differences in mathematics, and a fourth essay focused on gender but did not discuss performance in math.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Davies, Spencer, &amp; Steele, 2005</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/davies_spencer_steele/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/davies_spencer_steele/</guid>
      <description>Two studies examined the consequences of exposing women to stereotype-confirming television advertisements on pursuing leadership versus subordinate roles. In Experiment 1, male and female undergraduates highly-identified with math viewed a set of television commercials that had aired on national broadcasts. Half of the students saw a set of four non-stereotypic commercials (control), whereas the other half saw those four commercials and an additional two commercials showing women in stereotypic roles (one portraying a woman so excited about an acne product that she bounced with joy on her bed and another showing a female college student dreaming about becoming homecoming queen) (stereotype threat for women).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Davies, Spencer, Quinn, &amp; Gerhardstein, 2002</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/davies_spencer_quinn_gerhardstein/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/davies_spencer_quinn_gerhardstein/</guid>
      <description>Three studies examined whether stereotype threat might arise from exposure to stereotype-confirming messages in television advertisements. In Experiment 1, male and female undergraduates highly-identified with math viewed a set of six television commercials that had aired on national broadcasts. Half of the students saw a set where two of the commercials were stereotypic of women (one portraying a woman so excited about an acne product that she bounced with joy on her bed and another showing a woman excitedly anticipating eating brownies made with a new mix), and the other half saw two counter-stereotypic commercials (one showing a woman exhibiting detailed knowledge of automotive engineering and another depicting a woman speaking intelligently about her concerns regarding health care).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Davis, Aronson, &amp; Salinas, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/davis_aronson_salinas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/davis_aronson_salinas/</guid>
      <description>This study examined whether Black racial identity might moderate vulnerability to stereotype threat. Recent research on Black racial attitudes suggests that African-Americans conceptualize their racial identity in different ways, and the relative salience of various conceptualizations (termed statuses) can modulate inter-racial interactions. Pre-Encounter status tends to be associated with a de-emphasis or even denigration of being Black. Encounter status refers to an emphasis on race in one&amp;rsquo;s self-identity. Immersion-Emersion pertains to the celebration of Black identity and culture but includes denigration of Whites, and Internalization status refers to a strong Black racial identity that is non-exclusionary and egalitarian.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deaux, Bikman, Gilkes, Ventuneac, Joseph, Payne, &amp; Steele, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/deaux_bikman_gilkes_ventuneac_joseph_payen_steele/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/deaux_bikman_gilkes_ventuneac_joseph_payen_steele/</guid>
      <description>Two studies assessed stereotype threat in two generations of Afro-Caribbean immigrants. It was hypothesized that second-generation immigrants might be more likely to show performance decrements under race-based stereotype threat, given a presumed shift in the importance of one identity (i.e., West Indian) to another (i.e., African American)and the greater exposure to race-based prejudice in the second generation. In Study 1, students of West Indian origin completed a survey designed to measure the perceived favorability of stereotypes of West Indians and African Americans, the level of identification with each group, and expectations of discrimination.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Delgado &amp; Prieto, 2008</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/delgado_prieto/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/delgado_prieto/</guid>
      <description>This experiment focused on domain-specific anxiety as a mediator of stereotype threat. A large sample of boys and girls in Spanish high schools (N = 313) completed tests of mathematical ability and mental rotation (i.e., the ability to correctly judge the orientation of an object that has been rotated through the perceiver&amp;rsquo;s imagination) as well as a questionnaire designed to measure math anxiety focusing on &amp;ldquo;various psycho-physiological reactions, beliefs and behaviors related to the daily and academic use of mathematics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eriksson &amp; Lindholm, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/eriksson_lindholm/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/eriksson_lindholm/</guid>
      <description>This experiment examined math performance in a country, Sweden, that emphasizes gender equality. According to a recent analysis by the World Economic Forum, the gaps between men and women in Sweden on economic, political, education, and health variables are the smallest in the world. Swedish male and female undergraduate math and chemistry majors completed a difficult math test that, they were told, would allow comparison of their scores against those of the other students to assess their math ability.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ford, Ferguson, Brooks, &amp; Hagadone, 2004</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/ford_ferguson_brooks_hagadone/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/ford_ferguson_brooks_hagadone/</guid>
      <description>Two correlational studies examined the buffering role of coping sense of humor in stereotype threat. In Experiment 1, men and women undergraduates completed the Coping Humor Scale (CHS), a measure designed to assess the use of humor as a coping strategy for dealing with stressful situations and then answered two questions about how well they typically perform on math and verbal sections of standardized tests. For women, CHS scores were correlated with estimates of their math, but not their verbal, test performance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frantz, Cuddy, Burnett, Ray, &amp; Hart, 2004</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/frantz_cuddy_burnett_ray_hart/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/frantz_cuddy_burnett_ray_hart/</guid>
      <description>This study examines how White&amp;rsquo;s completion of an implicit measure of racial attitudes might actually present a risk of confirming the stereotype that Whites are racially biased. To test this notion, White undergraduates in Experiment 1 completed an implicit measure of race-based associations (the race Implicit Association Task (IAT); Greenwald, McGhee, &amp;amp; Schwartz, 1998) after being told nothing about the measure (control), that the measure indicated &amp;ldquo;racial bias&amp;rdquo; (high threat) or that responses to the measure reflected knowledge of, but not personal belief in, racial stereotypes (no threat).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goff, Steele, &amp; Davies, 2008</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/goff_steele_davies/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:12 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/goff_steele_davies/</guid>
      <description>Four experiments investigated the role of stereotype threat in affecting physical proximity during intergroup interactions. It was hypothesized that White individuals&amp;rsquo; fear of confirming the stereotype that Whites are racist would produce physical distancing during interracial interactions even in the absence of interracial animosity. In Experiment 1, White male undergraduates were told they would have a conversation with two other individuals. The race of these supposed conversation partners (depicted in photographs) was varied so that they were both either White or Black.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bosson, Haymovitz, &amp; Pinel, 2004</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/bosson_haymovitz_pinel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/bosson_haymovitz_pinel/</guid>
      <description>This study examined non-verbal indicators of anxiety under stereotype threat. To do so, heterosexual and gay men briefly interacted with children in a nursery school after either indicating their sexual orientation (stereotype threat for gay men, given the stereotype that homosexuals pose a risk for young children) or not. Self-reported anxiety following the interaction did not reveal differences between those who had indicated their sexual orientation versus those who had not.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brown &amp; Day, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/brown_day/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/brown_day/</guid>
      <description>This paper contributes to the literature examining the effects of stereotype threat on performance on Raven&amp;rsquo;s Advanced Progressive Matrices (APM) task, a non-verbal task that has been described as &amp;ldquo;culture-reduced&amp;rdquo; and a relatively &amp;ldquo;pure&amp;rdquo; measure of cognitive ability and reasoning (see Mayer &amp;amp; Hanges, 2003; McKay, Doverspike, Bowen-Hilton, &amp;amp; Martin, 2002). African-American and White undergraduates completed the APM after being given standard instructions that &amp;ldquo;the Advanced Progressive Matrices is a measure of observation and clear thinking&amp;rdquo; (standard), that it &amp;ldquo;is an IQ test&amp;hellip;frequently used to measure individuals’ intelligence and ability” (stereotype threat for African-Americans), or that it &amp;ldquo;is a series of puzzles&amp;rdquo; (low stereotype threat).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brown &amp; Josephs, 1999</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/brown_josephs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/brown_josephs/</guid>
      <description>Three experiments examined whether men and women have different concerns when confronting a difficult math test that might account for stereotype threat effects. In Experiment 1, male and female undergraduates completed a math test after being told either that the test was designed to &amp;ldquo;help us identify people who are exceptionally strong in their mathematical reasoning abilities&amp;rdquo; (hypothesized to produce stereotype threat for men) or &amp;ldquo;to identify people who are especially weak in their mathematical reasoning abilities&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for women).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brown &amp; Pinel, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/brown_pinel/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/brown_pinel/</guid>
      <description>This experiment examined the moderating role of stigma consciousness on stereotype threat. Stigma consciousness refers to differences in the degree that individuals are chronically aware and conscious of their stigmatized status. Whereas individuals low in stigma consciousness typically report that they are unaware of their stereotyped status when interacting with other people and assume that stereotypes will not affect them personally, individuals high in stigma consciousness expect others to interpret their behavior and to judge them through the lens of stereotypes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cadinu, Maass, Frigerio, Impagliazzo, &amp; Latinotti, 2003</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cadinu_maass_frigerio_impagliazzo_latinotti/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cadinu_maass_frigerio_impagliazzo_latinotti/</guid>
      <description>One reason that stereotype threat might interfere with performance is because it lowers expectations regarding performance which, in turn, undermines performance quality. Two studies examined the consequences of stereotype threat on expectations of performance. In Experiment 1, female undergraduates completed a math task after being told that on tasks of logical–mathematical abilities &amp;ldquo;women obtain lower scores than males&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat), &amp;ldquo;women obtain higher scores than males&amp;rdquo; (no stereotype threat) or that &amp;ldquo;no differences between men and women emerge&amp;rdquo; (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cadinu, Maass, Lombardo, &amp; Frigerio, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cadinu_maass_lombardo_frigerio/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cadinu_maass_lombardo_frigerio/</guid>
      <description>Individuals differ in the degree that they believe their experiences are caused by internal versus external causes. For individuals with a more Internal Locus of Control, their experiences and outcomes tend to be explained in terms of internal forces such as traits, ability, or effort. For individuals with a more External Locus of Control, events tend to be explained in terms of luck, fate, or others&amp;rsquo; actions. Although an Internal Locus of Control has generally been shown to predict higher effort and achievement, beliefs in internal causes might also make an individual more susceptible to stereotype threat.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cadinu, Maass, Rosabianca, &amp; Kiesner, 2005</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cadinu_maass_rosabianca_kiesner/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cadinu_maass_rosabianca_kiesner/</guid>
      <description>In this experiment, women undergraduate students were given a difficult math task after being told either that &amp;ldquo;there are clear differences in the scores obtained by men and woman&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat) or that &amp;ldquo;there are no differences between men and women&amp;rdquo; (control) in logical-mathematical tasks. Interspersed throughout the testing booklet were blank sheets on which students were encouraged to &amp;ldquo;write anything that comes to your mind.&amp;rdquo; These thought listings were classified by coders who were unaware of the students experimental condition as reflecting i) negative math related thoughts, ii) hatred of math, iii) general distress, iv) self-confidence, or v) neutral references to the test.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chasteen, Bhattacharyya, Horhota, Tam, &amp; Hasher, 2005</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/chasteen_bhattacharyya_horhota_tam_hasher/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/chasteen_bhattacharyya_horhota_tam_hasher/</guid>
      <description>Three studies examined the role of stereotype threat in accounting for memory deficits in older adults. Unlike previous studies on stereotype threat involved in memory and aging, these studies used socially involving stimuli and varied instructions that were given. In Experiment 1, older and younger adults read brief descriptions of behaviors supposedly performed by an individual (e.g., &amp;ldquo;had a party for some friends last week&amp;rdquo;) either while trying to form an impression of the person (impression formation set) or while trying to memorize the sentences (memory set).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cheryan &amp; Bodenhausen, 2000</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cheryan_bodenhausen/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cheryan_bodenhausen/</guid>
      <description>This study used a blatant manipulation to highlight for Asian-American females one of their social identities for which there exist opposing stereotype-based expectations of performance. Asian-American undergraduates highly identified in mathematics completed a task involving quantitative skills. Prior to performing the task, the women answered questions about the centrality and importance of their racial identity (race highlighted), their gender identity (gender highlighted), or about their personal identity (control). Performance was significantly worse in the racial identity compared with the control condition, but there was no significant difference between the control and the gender identity condition.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cohen &amp; Garcia, 2005</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cohen_garcia/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cohen_garcia/</guid>
      <description>Whereas stereotype threat involves an individual&amp;rsquo;s fear that he or she might behave in a manner that confirms a stereotype of one&amp;rsquo;s group, individuals might also show concern about the potential stereotype-confirming acts of other group members. This threat, termed collective threat, arises from the awareness that the poor performance of a single individual in one’s group might be viewed as stereotype-confirming and generalized to one’s group. A pilot questionnaire study confirmed that Black and Latino students reported more threat from collective threat and from being stereotyped than from stereotype threat.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cohen, Garcia, Apfel, &amp; Master, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cohen_garcia_apfel_master/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cohen_garcia_apfel_master/</guid>
      <description>This paper reports two field studies in which students were led to self-affirm to assess the consequences on academic performance. In these studies (separated by a year and comprised of a separate set of students), seventh grade students at a racially-diverse middle school in the Northeast U.S. were randomly assigned to self-affirm or not to self-affirm as part of a brief classroom exercise. Students who self-affirmed did so by indicating values that were important to them and writing a brief essay indicating why those values were important.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cohen, Steele, &amp; Ross, 1999</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cohen_steele_ross/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cohen_steele_ross/</guid>
      <description>These studies examined the consequences of critical feedback provided to White and Black students by a White mentor. Such situations are fraught with ambiguity when threatening feedback is provided to students who chronically face negative stereotypes about their group’s capacities. In Experiment 1, Black and White undergraduates received detailed, largely negative feedback from a White reviewer on an essay they had composed. This criticism was either provided without additional elaboration (unbuffered criticism), was accompanied by a comment generally praising the writer&amp;rsquo;s enthusiasm and general writing style (criticism + praise), or was prefaced with comments invoking high standards but also assurances that the student could meet those standards (criticism + standards + assurance).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cole, Matheson, &amp; Anisman, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cole_matheson_anisman/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/cole_matheson_anisman/</guid>
      <description>This correlation study examined academic performance of White and ethnic minority college students over the course of their first year at a predominantly White Canadian institution. A battery of measures were administered at the beginning, middle, and end of the students&amp;rsquo; first year, and students&amp;rsquo; grades were collected. Overall (and consistent with the presence of stereotype threat for minorities), ethnic minority students showed stronger ethnic identity, but also higher levels of avoidance goals and lower levels of perceived institutional academic support.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Croizet &amp; Claire, 1998</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/croizet_claire/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/croizet_claire/</guid>
      <description>This experiment demonstrated stereotype threat effects based on social class. University students completed a task involving verbal problems as part of a course exercise. Unbeknownst to the students, information was also solicited that allowed classification of students as low or high in socioeconomic status (SES) based on their parents&amp;rsquo; occupation and the level of financial assistance being provided for them to attend university. Prior to completing the verbal problems, the task was described as designed to &amp;ldquo;assess your intellectual ability for solving verbal problems&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat for low SES students) or to &amp;ldquo;test several hypotheses about the role attention plays in the functioning of lexical memory&amp;rdquo; (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adams, Garcia, Purdie-Vaughns, &amp; Steele, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/adams_garcia_purdie-vaughns_steele/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/adams_garcia_purdie-vaughns_steele/</guid>
      <description>Three experiments examined the effects of exposure to sexism on women&amp;rsquo;s task performance, self-esteem, and sense of belonging in an academic setting. In Experiment 1, female undergraduates who were about to participate in a study were told by another female student who supposedly was completing the study (actually, she was a confederate of the experimenter) either that the male experimenter was sexist (threat) or no mention was made of the experimenter&amp;rsquo;s attitudes towards women (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ambady, Paik, Steele, Owen-Smith, &amp; Mitchell, 2004</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/ambady_paik_steele_owen-smith_mitchell/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/ambady_paik_steele_owen-smith_mitchell/</guid>
      <description>Two experiments examined individuation processes as a buffer against stereotype threat. In Experiment 1, female undergraduates completed a task that highlighted their gender by presenting them with words on a computer screen related to women (stereotype threat ) or not related to women (control) below the level of conscious awareness. After this manipulation, half the students were asked to indicate their favorite food, movie, book, and hobbies and to list their three best and worst qualities (individuation condition) or answered a series of questions about topics unrelated to the self (non-individuation condition).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ambady, Shih, Kim, &amp; Pittinsky, 2001</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/ambady_shih_kim_pittinsky/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/ambady_shih_kim_pittinsky/</guid>
      <description>These studies focused in the emergence of stereotype threat in children. In Experiment 1, Asian-American girls ranging in age from kindergarten to 8th grade completed tasks that were intended to highlight their Asian identity, their female identity, or neither identity (control). Following these tasks, all girls completed items from a grade-appropriate standardized math test. Girls from lower-elementary and middle school grades showed a similar effect: math performance was bolstered when Asian identity had been made salient but harmed when female identity had been made salient.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Andreoletti &amp; Lachman, 2004</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/andreoletti_lachman/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/andreoletti_lachman/</guid>
      <description>This experiment examined the role of education as a buffer against stereotype threat regarding the elderly and memory performance. Young (average age 31.8 years), middle-aged (47.7 years), and old (69.4 years) normal functioning women and men were told they would complete several tasks involving memory. One-third of the participants were told that the tests revealed age differences (stereotype threat), one-third were told that the tests produce no age differences (stereotype invalidation), and one-third were told nothing about age difference on the test (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aronson &amp; Inzlicht, 2004</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/aronson_inzlicht/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/aronson_inzlicht/</guid>
      <description>These experiments examined self-assessments of ability and performance among Blacks who expected to be judged in terms of racial stereotypes. In Experiment 1, Black and White undergraduates were asked to complete items from the verbal section of the GRE exam and to indicate the likelihood that each response was correct. Blacks who indicated that they often expect to be judged in stereotypical terms performed more poorly but were more likely to indicate that their responses were correct than those who did not expect to be stereotyped.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aronson, Fried, &amp; Good, 2002</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/aronson_fried_good/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/aronson_fried_good/</guid>
      <description>In this experiment, White and Black students were assigned to one of three conditions to assess the impact of an intervention designed to reduce stereotype threat. In two conditions, students were asked to write a letter of encouragement to a younger student who was experiencing academic struggles. In one of these conditions, students were prompted to endorse a view of intelligence as malleable, &amp;ldquo;like a muscle&amp;rdquo; that can grow with work and effort.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aronson, Jannone, McGlone, &amp; Johnson-Campbell, In Press</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/aronson_jannone_mcglone_johnson-campbell/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/aronson_jannone_mcglone_johnson-campbell/</guid>
      <description>In this experiment, high achieving White and African-American undergraduates were asked to think about a prominent politician from the 2008 presidential campaign before completing a difficult verbal exam that had been described as diagnostic of ability. Immediately prior to taking the exam, participants were given several pictures of John McCain, Barack Obama, or no photographs (control) along with identical quotes attributed to each individual or to &amp;ldquo;an American politician&amp;rdquo; (control). Participants in these conditions were then asked to list two benefits of a McCain presidency, two benefits of an Obama presidency, or, in the control condition, the benefits of being politically informed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aronson, Lustina, Good, Keough, Steele, &amp; Brown, 1999</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/aronson_lustina_good_keough_steele_brown/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/aronson_lustina_good_keough_steele_brown/</guid>
      <description>The two experiments reported in this paper demonstrate that stereotype threat is a general phenomenon that can be experienced by members of any group depending on context. In Experiment 1, White males with high math SAT scores took a difficult math test. In one condition, students were given information suggesting that Asians typically outperform other students in math. Moreover, the students in this condition were told that the study was designed to identify the nature and scope of differences in performance between Asians and other groups in mathematics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beaton, Tougas, Rinfret, Huard, &amp; Delisle, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/beaton_tougas_rinfret_huard_delisle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/beaton_tougas_rinfret_huard_delisle/</guid>
      <description>Two experiments investigated the roles of stereotype activation and anxiety in accounting for the performance of women in mathematics under stereotype threat. In Experiment 1, female undergraduates who identified strongly with the domain of math answered a set of math problems by themselves (control), in the presence of five other male students (solo condition), or in a mixed-gender group (non-solo condition). After being told they were to complete a series of math problems but before doing so, students completed word fragments designed to assess gender stereotype activation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beilock, Jellison, Rydell, McConnell, &amp; Carr, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/beilock_jellison_rydell_mcconnell_carr/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/beilock_jellison_rydell_mcconnell_carr/</guid>
      <description>These studies focused in the effects of stereotype threat on the performance of highly proceduralized activities. Unlike many tasks that rely on availability of attention and allocation of working memory capacity, performance on highly proceduralized skills can be harmed by increasing attention and cognitive involvement. Experiment 1 involved expert golfers who performed a putting test after being told either that &amp;ldquo;women actually tend to perform better than men on our putting task&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat) or that &amp;ldquo;this research was investigating individual differences in golf putting performance&amp;rdquo; (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beilock, Rydell, &amp; McConnell, 2007</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/beilock_rydell_mcconnell/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/beilock_rydell_mcconnell/</guid>
      <description>This paper examines whether stereotype threat might reduce performance by imposing demands on the phonological component of the working memory system. If stereotype threat produces worries and concerns about the task at hand, then these worries might interfere with the part of working memory that is responsible for storing task-relevant verbal information. In Experiment 1, male and female math-identified participants completed easy and difficult tasks involving modular arithmetic under stereotype threat (with the study described as assessing &amp;ldquo;why men are generally better than women at math&amp;rdquo;) or no stereotype threat (with the study assessing &amp;ldquo;why some people are better at math than are others&amp;rdquo;).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ben-Zeev, Fein, &amp; Inzlicht, 2005</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/ben-zeev_fein_inzlicht/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/ben-zeev_fein_inzlicht/</guid>
      <description>Two experiments examined the role of arousal in accounting for underperformance under stereotype threat. In Experiment 1, male and female students who were highly identified with mathematics were told that they would take a difficult math test. Half the students were told that there were typically no gender differences in performance on the test (no threat condition) whereas the other half were told nothing about the test (stereotype threat condition). After being told about the upcoming test, students either completed an easy task (wrote their name as many times as they could for 20 seconds) or a novel, difficult task (wrote their name backward as many times as they could for 20 seconds).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bergeron, Block and Echtenkamp, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/bergeron_block_echtenkamp/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/bergeron_block_echtenkamp/</guid>
      <description>This study examines the affect of gender-based stereotype threat on managerial performance. Male and female graduate students were asked to complete a lengthy exercise in which they made a series of decisions regarding personnel issues as though they were a senior manager in a human resources department, a stereotypically male position. Before beginning this exercise, the students were informed that the person who had previously held the position of senior manager was either a man who was described with stereotypically masculine traits (stereotype threat for women) or a woman described with stereotypically feminine traits (no stereotype threat).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blanton, Crocker, &amp; Miller, 2000</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/blanton_crocker_miller/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/blanton_crocker_miller/</guid>
      <description>This study examined the consequences of different kinds of social comparisons under stereotype threat. Whereas comparisons with superior ingroup members typically lead to lowered state self-esteem, it was suggested that such comparisons might elevate state self-esteem when the superior ingroup member is viewed as challenging stereotypes. To test this hypothesis, female African-American students participated in a study in which they were put under stereotype threat by being told that &amp;ldquo;the study was to standardize a new IQ measure of natural math ability.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blascovich, Spencer, Quinn, &amp; Steele, 2001</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/blascovich_spencer_quinn_steele/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/blascovich_spencer_quinn_steele/</guid>
      <description>This experiment examined the effect of stereotype threat on arterial blood pressure. Black and White undergraduates were asked to complete a test supposedly designed to assess intelligence under one of two conditions. In one condition, a White professor discussed the debate regarding racial bias in standardized tests and indicated that the test items here were part of an attempt to develop a new intelligence test (stereotype threat for Blacks). In a second condition, a Black professor also discussed racial bias in testing but indicated that the items were from a test that had already been shown to be culturally unbiased (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Abrams, Eller, &amp; Bryant, 2006</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/abrams_eller_bryant/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 18:12:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/bibliography/abrams_eller_bryant/</guid>
      <description>This experiment examined intergroup attitudes as a moderator of stereotype threat. Male and female adults from 59-89 years of age (average age = 74.8 yrs) completed a test after being told either &amp;ldquo;it is widely assumed that intellectual performance declines with age, so the purpose of this study is to see whether old people do perform&amp;rdquo; (stereotype threat) or &amp;ldquo;to see how people differ in their responses on different tasks&amp;rdquo; (control).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>History</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/about/history/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 17:06:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/about/history/</guid>
      <description>Before 2017 For years Catherine Good (Baruch College) and Steve Stroessner (Barnard College) maintained www.reducingstereotypethreat.org. It consisted of an annotated bibliography of research on stereotype threat, along with discussions of various aspects of stereotype threat (e.g. vulnerable groups, situations, mechanisms, &amp;hellip;). This made it an indispensable resource for learning about stereotype threat and then teaching it to others. When training teaching assistants, I would send them to the site to explore specific questions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Legacy (before 2017)</title>
      <link>https://garcias.github.io/about/legacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2018 15:04:16 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://garcias.github.io/about/legacy/</guid>
      <description>The original Reducingstereotypethreat.org had the following description and acknowledgments.
About Reducing Stereotype Threat Reducingstereotypethreat.org was created by two social psychologists as a resource for faculty, teachers, students, and the general public interested in the phenomenon of stereotype threat. This website offers summaries of research on stereotype threat and discusses unresolved issues and controversies in the research literature. Included are some research-based suggestions for reducing the negative consequences of stereotyping, particularly in academic settings.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>